<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!-- This template is for creating an Internet Draft using xml2rfc,
     which is available here: http://xml.resource.org. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY RFC3424 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3424.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC4690 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4690.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5218 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5218.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5891 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5891.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC5895 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5895.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7228 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7228.xml">
<!ENTITY RFC7305 PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7305.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.iab-filtering-considerations PUBLIC ''
    'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.iab-filtering-considerations.xml'>
]>
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- used by XSLT processors -->
<!-- For a complete list and description of processing instructions (PIs),
     please see http://xml.resource.org/authoring/README.html. -->
<!-- Below are generally applicable Processing Instructions (PIs) that most I-Ds might want to use.
     (Here they are set differently than their defaults in xml2rfc v1.32) -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- give errors regarding ID-nits and DTD validation -->
<!-- control the table of contents (ToC) -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<!-- generate a ToC -->
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<!-- the number of levels of subsections in ToC. default: 3 -->
<!-- control references -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<!-- use symbolic references tags, i.e, [RFC2119] instead of [1] -->
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- sort the reference entries alphabetically -->
<!-- control vertical white space
     (using these PIs as follows is recommended by the RFC Editor) -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<!-- do not start each main section on a new page -->
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- keep one blank line between list items -->
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<rfc category="info" docName="draft-iab-protocol-transitions-00.txt"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <!-- category values: std, bcp, info, exp, and historic
     ipr values: full3667, noModification3667, noDerivatives3667
     you can add the attributes updates="NNNN" and obsoletes="NNNN"
     they will automatically be output with "(if approved)" -->

  <!-- ***** FRONT MATTER ***** -->

  <front>
    <!-- The abbreviated title is used in the page header - it is only necessary if the
         full title is longer than 39 characters -->

    <title abbrev="Planning for Transition">Out With the Old and In With the New: Planning for Protocol Transitions</title>

    <!--add 'role="editor"' below for the editors if appropriate -->

    <author initials="D." surname="Thaler" fullname="Dave Thaler">
          <organization>Microsoft</organization>
          <address>
            <postal>
              <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
              <city>Redmond</city>
              <region>WA</region>
              <code>98052</code>
              <country>US</country>
            </postal>
            <email>dthaler@microsoft.com</email>
          </address>
        </author>

    <date/>

    <!-- If the month and year are both specified and are the current ones, xml2rfc will fill
         in the current day for you. If only the current year is specified, xml2rfc will fill
     in the current day and month for you. If the year is not the current one, it is
     necessary to specify at least a month (xml2rfc assumes day="1" if not specified for the
     purpose of calculating the expiry date).  With drafts it is normally sufficient to
     specify just the year. -->

    <!-- Meta-data Declarations -->

    <area>General</area>

    <workgroup>Internet Architecture Board</workgroup>

    <!-- WG name at the upperleft corner of the doc,
         IETF is fine for individual submissions.
     If this element is not present, the default is "Network Working Group",
         which is used by the RFC Editor as a nod to the history of the IETF. -->

    <abstract>
      <t> Over the many years since the introduction of the Internet Protocol,
          we have seen a number of transitions, throughout the protocol stack,
          from one protocol or technology to another.  Many protocols and
          technologies were not designed to enable smooth transition to
          alternatives or to easily deploy extensions, and thus some transitions,
          such as the introduction of IPv6, have been difficult.  This document
          attempts to summarize some basic principles to enable future transitions,
          and also summarizes what makes for a good transition plan.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>

    <section title="Introduction" anchor="intro">
      <t> A "transition" is "the process or period of changing from one state
          or condition to another.  There are several types of such transitions,
          including both technical transitions (e.g., changing protocols or
          deploying an extension) and organizational transitions (e.g., changing
          what organization manages the IETF web site, or the RFC production center).
          This document focuses solely on technical transitions, although some
          principles might apply to other types as well.
      </t>
      <t> There have been many IETF and IAB RFCs and IAB statements discussing
          transitions of various sorts.  Most are protocol-specific documents
          about specific transitions.  For example, some relevant ones in which
          the IAB has been involved include:
      </t>
      <t><list style="symbols">
          <t> IAB RFC 3424 <xref target="RFC3424"/> recommended that any technology
              for so-called "unilateral self-address fixing (UNSAF)" across NATs
              include an exit strategy to transition away from such a mechanism.
              Since the IESG, not the IAB, approves IETF documents, the IESG
              thus became the body to enforce (or not) such a requirement.
          </t>
          <t> IAB RFC 4690 <xref target="RFC4690"/> gave recommendations around
              internationalized domain names. It discussed issues around the process
              of transitioning to new versions of Unicode, and this resulted in the
              creation of the IETF Precis WG to address this problem.
          </t>
          <t> The IAB statement on "Follow-up-work on NAT-PT"
              <xref target="IabIpv6TransitionStatement"/> pointed out gaps at the time
              in transitioning to IPv6, and this resulted in the rechartering of the
              IETF Behave WG to solve this problem.
          </t>
      </list></t>
      <t> More recently, the IAB has done work on more generally applicable principles,
          including two RFCs.
      </t>
      <t> IAB RFC 5218 <xref target="RFC5218"/> on "What Makes for a Successful Protocol?"
          studied specifically what factors contribute to, and detract from,
          the success of a protocol and it made a number of recommendations.  It
          discussed two types of transitions: "initial success" (the transition
          to the technology) and extensibility (the transition to updated
          versions of it).  The principles and recommendations in that document
          are generally applicable to all technical transitions. Some important principles 
          included:
      </t>
      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t> Incentive: Transition is easiest when the benefits come to those bearing the costs.
              That is, the benefits should outweigh the costs at *each* entity.
              Some successful cases did this by providing incentives (e.g., tax breaks),
              or by reducing costs (e.g., freely available source), or by imposing
              costs of not transitioning (e.g., regulation), or even by narrowing
              the scenarios of applicability to just the cases where benefits do    
              outweigh costs at all relevant entities.
          </t>
          <t> Incremental Deployability: Backwards compatibility makes transition easier.
              Furthermore, transition is easiest when changing only one entity still
              benefits that entity.  In the easiest case, the benefit immediately
              outweighs the cost and so entities are naturally incented to transition.
              More commonly, the benefits only outweigh the costs once a significant
              number of other entities also transition.  Unfortunately, in such cases,
              the natural incentive is often to delay transitioning.
          </t>
          <t> Total Cost: Don't underestimate the cost of things other than the
              hardware/software itself.  For example, operational tools and processes,
              personnel training, business model (accounting/billing) dependencies,
              and legal (regulation, patents, etc.) costs all add up.
          </t>
          <t> Extensibility: Design for extensibility so that things can be fixed up later.
          </t>
      </list></t>
      <t> IAB RFC 7305 <xref target="RFC7305"/> reported on a IAB workshop
          on Internet Technology Adoption and Transition (ITAT).  Like
          RFC 5218, this workshop also discussed economic aspects of transition,
          not just technical aspects.  Some important observations included:
      </t>
      <t><list style="numbers">
          <t> Early-Adopter Incentives: Part of Bitcoin's strategy was extra incentives
              for early adopters compared to late adopters.  That is, providing a long-term 
              advantage to early
              adopters can help stimulate transition even when the initial costs outweigh
              the initial benefit.
          </t>
          <t> Policy Partners: Policy-making organizations of various sorts (RIRs,
              ICANN, etc.) can be important partners in enabling and facilitating
              transition.
          </t>
      </list></t>
      <t> The remainder of this document continues the discussion in those two RFCs
          and provides some additional thoughts on the topic of transition strategies
          and plans.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Transition vs. Co-existence" anchor="coexist">
        <t> We need to distinguish between a strict "flag-day" style transition where an 
            old mechanism
            is immediately replaced with a new mechanism, vs. a looser co-existence based
            approach where transition proceeds in stages where a new mechanism is first
            added alongside an existing one for some overlap period, and then the old
            mechanism is removed at a later stage.
        </t>
        <t> When a new mechanism is backwards compatible with an existing mechanism, transition is
            easiest, and the difference between the two types of transition is not 
            particularly significant.
            However, when no backwards compatibility exists (such as in the IPv4 to IPv6 transition),
            a transition plan must choose either a "flag day" or a period of co-existence.
            When a large number of entities are involved, a flag day becomes impractical.
            Coexistence, on the other hand, involves additional costs of maintaining two
            separate mechanisms during the overlap period which could be quite long.
            Furthermore, the longer the overlap period, the more the old mechanism might
            get further deployment and thus increase the overall pain of transition.
        </t>
        <t> Often the decision between a "flag day" and a sustained co-existence period
            may be difficult, such as in the case of IDNA2008 
            <xref target="RFC5891"/>
            <xref target="RFC5895"/>
            and Unicode TR46
            <xref target="TR46"/>.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Translation/Adaptation Location">
        <t> A translation or adaptation layer is often required if the old and new
            mechanisms are not interoperable.  Care must be taken when determining
            where such a translator is best placed. 
        </t>
        <t> Requiring a translator in the middle of the path can hamper end-to-end
            security and reliability.  For example, see the discussion of 
            network-based filtering in <xref target="I-D.iab-filtering-considerations"/>.
        </t>
        <t> On the other hand, requiring a translation layer within an
            endpoint can be a resource issue in some cases, such as if the endpoint
            could be a constrained node <xref target="RFC7228"/>.
        </t>
        <t> Any transition strategy for a non-backward-compatible mechanism should 
            include a discussion of where it is placed and a rationale.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="Translation Plans">
        <t> A good transition plan includes at least the following components:
        </t>
        <t><list style="numbers">
            <t> An explanation of incentives for each entity involved
            </t>
            <t> A description of transition phases.  For example, there might
                be pilot, co-existence, deprecation, and removal phases for
                a transition from one technology to another incompatible one.
            </t>
            <t> A proposed timeline
            </t>
            <t> A way to effectively communicate the proposed plan to the
                entities affected, and incorporate their feedback
            </t>
        </list></t>
    </section>

    <section title="Security Considerations" anchor="security">
        <t> This document discusses attributes of protocol transitions.  Some
            types of transition can adversely affect security or privacy.  For
            example, requiring a translator in the middle of the path may hamper
            end-to-end security and privacy, since it creates an attractive target.
            For further discussion of some of these issues, see Section 5 of
            <xref target="I-D.iab-filtering-considerations"/>.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IANA Considerations">
        <t> This document requires no actions by the IANA.
        </t>
    </section>

    <section title="IAB Members at the Time of This Writing">
        <figure>
            <artwork>
Jari Arkko
Mary Barnes
Marc Blanchet
Ralph Droms
Ted Hardie
Joe Hildebrand
Russ Housley
Erik Nordmark
Robert Sparks
Andrew Sullivan
Dave Thaler
Brian Trammell
Suzanne Woolf
            </artwork>
        </figure>
    </section>

  </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <references title="Informative References">
      &RFC3424;
      &RFC4690;
      &RFC5218;
      &RFC5891;
      &RFC5895;
      &RFC7228;
      &RFC7305;
      &I-D.iab-filtering-considerations;

      <reference anchor="IabIpv6TransitionStatement"
                 target="https://www.iab.org/documents/correspondence-reports-documents/docs2007/follow-up-work-on-nat-pt//">
        <front>
          <title>Follow-up work on NAT-PT</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IAB</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2007" month="October" day="10"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

      <reference anchor="TR46"
                 target="http://www.unicode.org/reports/tr46/">
        <front>
          <title>Unicode IDNA Compatibility Processing</title>
          <author>
            <organization>Unicode Consortium</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2015" month="June" day="2"/>
        </front>
      </reference>

    </references>
  </back>
</rfc>
