<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- This line is a comment that won't appear in the generated document. -->
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd"[
      <!-- For each RFC you want to reference, add a line like below and then
           see the references section at the end.  This line tells the
           tool to pull the reference from the database. -->
      <!ENTITY rfc2119 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
      <!ENTITY rfc3972 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3972.xml">
      <!ENTITY rfc4941 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4941.xml">
      <!ENTITY rfc4944 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4944.xml">
      <!ENTITY rfc6282 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6282.xml">
      <!ENTITY rfc6724 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6724.xml">
      <!ENTITY rfc6775 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6775.xml">
      <!ENTITY rfc6973 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6973.xml">
      <!ENTITY rfc7217 SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7217.xml">
      <!-- For each Internet Draft you want to reference, add a line like
           below and then see the references section at the end. -->
      <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-6man-ipv6-address-generation-privacy PUBLIC ''
          'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6man-ipv6-address-generation-privacy.xml'>
      <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-6man-default-iids PUBLIC ''
          'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6man-default-iids.xml'>
      <!ENTITY I-D.ietf-6man-stable-privacy-addresses PUBLIC ''
          'http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6man-stable-privacy-addresses.xml'>
      ]>
<?rfc toc='yes' ?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes' ?>
<?rfc sortrefs='no'?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<!-- <?rfc-ext parse-xml-in-artwork='yes' ?> -->
<!-- <?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?> -->

<rfc docName="draft-thaler-6lo-privacy-addrs-00" ipr="trust200902" category="std">
  <front>
    <title abbrev='6LoWPAN Privacy Addresses'>Enabling Privacy Addressing With 6LoWPAN Technologies</title>
    <author initials='D.' surname='Thaler' fullname='Dave Thaler'>
      <organization>Microsoft</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>One Microsoft Way</street>
          <city>Redmond</city>
          <region>WA</region>
          <code>98052</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>dthaler@microsoft.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date year='2015' />
    <area>Internet</area>
    <keyword>unlinkability</keyword>
    <keyword>anonymity</keyword>
    <keyword>IPv6</keyword>
    <keyword>Secure Neighbor Discovery</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t> A potentially common misconception is that header 6LowPAN header compression is incompatible (or at least
          inefficient) with the notion of using addresses with sufficient entropy.  This draft attempts to dispel 
          that notion, and specifies how privacy addressing can be used on 6LoWPAN technologies, without
          additional overhead in data packets.
      </t>
    </abstract>
  </front>
  
  <middle>
    <section title='Introduction'>
      <t> RFC 6973 <xref target='RFC6973'/> discusses privacy considerations for Internet protocols, and Section 5.2
          in particular covers a number of privacy-specific threats.  In the context of IPv6 address,
          Section 3 of <xref target='I-D.ietf-6man-ipv6-address-generation-privacy'/> provides further
          elaboration on the applicability of the privacy threats.  When interface identifiers (IIDs) are
          generated without sufficient entropy, devices and users become vulnerable to
          the various threats discussed there, including correlation of activities over time, location tracking,
          address scanning, and device-specific vulnerability exploitation.
      </t>
      <t> Interfaces identifiers formed from IEEE identifiers can have insufficient entropy unless the
          IEEE identifier itself has sufficient entropy, has enough (typically 64 or more) bits of entropy 
          carried over into the IPv6 address to have a sufficiently large "anonymity set" as defined
          in <xref target='RFC6973'/>.  Furthermore, IEEE-identifier-based IIDs are also insufficient to
          prevent location tracking unless the IEEE identifier itself is different at each network location.
          This observation suggests that the privacy threats can be mitigated in either of two ways:
          either make sure the IEEE identifier contains 64 bits of entropy and is changed if a device moves
          to a different network, or else use an IPv6 address generation mechanism that is not IEEE-identifier-based.
      </t>
      <t> Furthermore, to mitigate the threat of correlation of activities over time, <xref target='RFC4941'/>
          specifies the notion of a "temporary" address to be used for sessions that should not be linkable
          to more permanent identifiers (such as a DNS name or stable hardware address).  Such temporary addresses
          are appropriate for connections (typically locally-initiated outbound sessions) that do not use a 
          stable identifier at a higher layer, such as a user name or hostname.  Indeed, the default
          address selection rules <xref target='RFC6724'/> now prefer temporary addresses by default for
          outgoing connections.  A new temporary address is periodically (default is 1 day in xref target='RFC4941'/>)
          generated, which limits the threat of correlation of activies over time to that period.  The address itself
          though may still be usable for existing long-lived connections (but not new connections) for
          some longer period (default is 1 week); this allows for not breaking application sessions, especially
          those that might be initiated shortly before a new temporary address is generated.  This fact means
          that multiple temporary addresses will exist at the same time, one for new connections, and one or more
          (often up to 6, per the default periods) old ones for long-lived connections.  This is in addition to
          zero or more "stable" addresses that might be used for connections that are linkable to more permanent
          identifiers such as DNS names or user names.
      </t>
      <t> There has been some concern that such approaches would necessarily interfere with efficient header
          compression for IPv6 over IEEE 802.15.4-based networks <xref target='RFC6282'/>, as it is important
          to keep data packets small on such networks.  This document specifies how to use such addresses
          on these networks while avoiding extra overhead.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title='Terminology'>
      <t> This document uses the terminology defined in Section 3 of <xref target='RFC6973'/>, including
          terms such as "(un)linkability" and "anonymity set".
      </t>
      <t>  The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
           "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
           document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target='RFC2119'/>.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title='Details'>
      <t> RFC 6282 <xref target='RFC6282'/> defines a method for deriving IIDs from the source and/or 
          destination addresses in the encapsulation header.  Unicast IPv6 addresses may be compressed 
          to 64, 16, or 0 bits in the encoded IPv6 header.
      </t>
      <t> A stable per-network random ID generation mechanism could be at layer 2 and that essentially becomes 
          another variant way to implement <xref target='I-D.ietf-6man-stable-privacy-addresses'/> if it's 
          64 bits of entropy.   An IID generated from a random 16-bit address per 
          Section 3.2.2 of <xref target='RFC6973'/> is not sufficient to mitigate address scanning, and also
          does not sufficiently increase the size of the "anonymity set" defined in <xref target='RFC6973'/>.
          The size of the address scan search space depends on the entropy in the IID.  An
          adversary could also use statisical methods to determine the size of the L2 address space and 
          thereby make some inference regarding the underlying technology on a given link.
      </t>
      <t> However, either way it doesn't expand the packet if there's 0 address bits in the packet.
      </t>
      <t> Second paragraph of introduction... Here's a cross reference
          <xref target='I-D.ietf-6man-default-iids'/>
          and
          And here's a bulleted list:
      </t>
      <t><list style='symbols'> 
          <t> First bullet.
          </t>
          <t> Second bullet.
          </t>
        </list>
      </t>
      <t> Now here's a sample ASCII art figure.
      </t>
      <figure align="center" anchor="processes">
          <artwork><![CDATA[
              +------------+
              |  Holder of |     1. Generation
              | identifier +<---------+
              +----+-------+          |
                   |                  | Match
                   |                  v/
                   |          +-------+-------+
                   +----------+ Repository of |
                   |          |  identifiers  |
                   |          +-------+-------+
   2. Distribution |                  ^\
                   |                  | Match
                   v                  |
         +---------+-------+          |
         |      User of    |          |
         |    identifier   +----------+
         +-----------------+    3. Use
        ]]></artwork>
        <postamble>Typical Identifier Processes
        </postamble>
      </figure>
    </section>

    <section title='Some Level 1 Title' anchor='somesection'>
      <t> Here's a numbered list:
      </t>
      <t><list style='numbers'>
         <t> First numbered item.
         </t>
         <t> Second numbered item.
         </t>
      </list>
      </t>

      <section title='Some Level 2 Title' anchor='somesubsection'>
        <t> Here's a glossary style list of terms.
        </t>
        <t><list style='hanging' hangIndent='2'>
          <t hangText='Widget:'> <vspace />
            Some description of a widget.
          </t> 
          <t hangText='Foobar:'> <vspace />
            Some definition of a foobar.
          </t>
        </list> 
        </t>
      </section>

      <section title='Another Level 2 Title'>
        <t> This section needs no anchor since there's no cross-reference
            to it from elsewhere, unlike <xref target='somesection'/>
            and <xref target='somesubsection'/>.
        </t>
        <t> Here's a sample packet diagram.
        </t>
        <figure align="center" anchor="tlv">
            <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[
                         1                   2                   3
     0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
    |     Type      |    Length     |            Value              |
    +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
            ]]></artwork>
            <postamble>Type Length Value Packet</postamble>
        </figure>
      </section>
    </section>

    <section title='IANA Considerations'>
      <t> This document has no actions for IANA.
      </t>
    </section>

    <section title='Security Considerations'>
      <t> This entire document is about security considerations and mitigations.
      </t>
    </section>
  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title='Normative References'>
      &rfc2119;
      &rfc4944;
      &rfc6282;
      &rfc6775;

    </references>
    
    <references title='Informative References'>
      &rfc3972;
      &rfc4941;
      &rfc6724;
      &rfc6973;
      &rfc7217;
      &I-D.ietf-6man-ipv6-address-generation-privacy;
      &I-D.ietf-6man-default-iids;
      &I-D.ietf-6man-stable-privacy-addresses;
    </references>

  </back>
</rfc>
